<chapter id="gametree">
<title>Game Tree Window</title>

<section>
<title>General</title>

<para>
The game tree window shows the variations of the current game as a tree
of nodes.
</para>
<para>
Nodes are displayed as black or white stones.
A symbol containing four small stones is used for nodes
containing setup stones and a gray diamond for other nodes.
Nodes containing a comment have a small blue line below the node.
The current node is marked with a blue background square.
You can change the size of the nodes and their labels from the
<guimenu>View</guimenu>/<guisubmenu>Tree</guisubmenu> menu of the menu bar
</para>
<para>
When a node is clicked on, the shortest path from the current node to the
target node is computed, and a series of <command>undo</command>
and <command>play</command> commands is sent to the Go program
to go there.
</para>
<para>
The context menu for a node allows the user to expand or hide subtrees
and to display node information and subtree statistics.
</para>
<para>
<note>
<simpara>
When large game trees are displayed and edited, the necessary updating of the
game tree can be very slow.
If this is the case, close the game tree window, if you don't need it,
or avoid that too many nodes are shown in the window.
You can hide nodes by using the <guimenuitem>Hide Subtree</guimenuitem>
and <guimenuitem>Hide Others</guimenuitem> menu items from the context
menu.
</simpara>
</note>
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Special Keys</title>

<para>
The arrow keys can be used to scroll the view.
In addition the following keys are defined:
</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><keycap>Home</keycap></term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Scroll to current node.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo></term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Open popup menu on current node.
On Mac OS X, the Apple key is used instead of <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>
<!-- Empty paragraph to enforce some space in JEditorPane (Java 1.5.0) -->
</para>

</section>

</chapter>
