<appendix id="news">
<title>Release Notes</title>
<para>
<revhistory>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.4.3</revnumber>
<date>09 Mar 2012</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix broken thumbnail generation on Unix if file name contained
non-ASCII characters.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Changed Back to Main Variation to go to the last move in the main
variation that had a variation, not to the last position in the main
variation.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Workaround for bad taskbar title (java-lang-Thread instead of GoGui)
with Gnome 3
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
No longer install the gogui-C.omf documentation metadata file on Unix,
which was the likely cause of problems with the system-wide help system
on some Linux distributions.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Updated toolbar icon for play command
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.4.2</revnumber>
<date>12 Oct 2011</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fixed bug in Unix install script introduced in version 1.4.1 that made it fail
when installing the Gnome 3 thumbnailer and the share/thumbnailers directory
did not already exist.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.4.1</revnumber>
<date>11 Oct 2011</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Set file status to modified and enable Save menu item if a label or markup was
added or changed.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Removed numbers in list menu items (like Recent Files) if the platform
is Mac because no mnemonics are used on the Mac.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
No longer use window titles in alert dialogs.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Removed duplicate menu access keys
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Avoid unjustified warnings (on standard error) about duplicate access keys in
menu items.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Make registering thumbnailer for SGF files work in Gnome 3.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.4.0</revnumber>
<date>08 Aug 2011</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Workaround for exception thrown at startup when GoGui is used with Java
1.7.0 (bug #3388086)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
No longer support switching the language in "Help/Switch language".
The language is now always set according to the default system language.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The mnemonic keys in the menu labels are now parsed from the language
resource files using the Qt convention (the mnemonic is marked with a
preceding '&#38;'). This avoids that non-English languages use the menmonics
from the English labels that may not exist in the non-English label.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-twogtp: new option -debugtocomment
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
No longer display a warning if the Go engine sends empty lines outside
responses, which is allowed by GTP (version 2, draft 2, section 2.9).
Fixes bug #3351774.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Show meaningful error messages when compiling GoGui with ant and the local
copies of the Docbook DTD or XSL files are not found.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Added German translation of the Windows installer.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The Windows installer now optionally installs the source code of GoGui.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New option -s for the Unix install script to specify sysconfdir.
Default changed to /usr/local/etc.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.3.0</revnumber>
<date>25 Mar 2011</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The checkbox menu item "View/Variation Labels" was replaced by a submenu
with the items "Children", "Siblings", "None"
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item: View/Move Numbers
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Ignore leading '>' characters when importing text positions to support
quotations in emails
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Assume that non-square positions are anchored at lower-left corner when
importing text positions
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The Windows installer now installs exe wrappers for the GoGui jar files
(created with Launch4j, see ant targets nsis and l4j).
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-terminal: New command line option -color
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-twogtp: New command line option -threads
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The Docbook XSL stylesheets are no longer included in the GoGui sources.
To compile GoGui, they need to be installed on the system.
The location of the directory can be given with the ant option
-Ddocbook-xsl.dir=directory.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The full Quaqua sources are no longer included in compiled GoGui distributions,
only the file quaqua.jar. GoGui can be compiled without Quaqua with the
ant option -Dquaqua.ignore=true
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
A source distribution of GoGui that contains no bytecode files can be
created with the new ant target dist-src.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
<date>28 Feb 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use more meaningful system properties for displaying the Java runtime name
and version in the about and crash dialog
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Look for strings like "Black to play" when importing positions from text
diagrams.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp: use a lock file to check that TwoGtp is not already running with the
same result file.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp: write game number to standard error at beginning of a game, if option
-verbose is used.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item Find Next Comment
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix parsing of OT property in SGF files that erroneously interpreted Japanese
byoyomi as Canadian overtime (which is currently the only time system supported
by GTP and GoGui)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Allow to use Reattach Parameters if program is dead but parameter snapshot
exists
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGuiAdapter: forward kgs-genmove_cleanup to the program if it supports it
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Add notes about OpenJDK and Ubuntu 9.10 in the README file.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Don't synchronize the program with GTP commands immediately after navigation
in the game tree but only when needed. This speeds up navigation and keeps
the GTP log shorter.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Simplify context menu of a point on the board by removing analyze commands
with point argument
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Support multi-line text in analyze commands of type gfx
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New checkbox Reuse text window in analyze dialog
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item: Import SGF from Clipboard
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu items: Snapshot Parameters, Restore Parameters
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Enable parameter commands in menu only if the currently attached program
has analyze commands of type "param"
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
System look and feel is now used by default on Linux, since the GTK-based
system look and feel in newer versions on the JRE has good usability now;
the JGoodies Looks look and feel is no longer used
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
No longer install MIME type definition for KDE 3 in installation script on
Unix; new version of KDE now support the standard shared MIME database from
freedesktop.org
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Default installation directory in install.sh is now /usr/local
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
<date>09 Jul 2008</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use Java 5 language features; older Java versions are no longer supported.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Remove the GmpToGtp adapter, because the Go Modem Protocol and usage of
serial ports have become quite obsolete. Should there still be use cases, then
a version of GmpToGtp from previous GoGui releases can still be used in
combination with a newer version of the GoGui interface.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use uppercase letters for color arguments in GTP commands (like play or
gogui-setup). This was changed for consistency with the convention in the user
interface. It could break programs that do not treat colors in a
case-insensitive way (in violation of the GTP specification). Such programs can
still be used by wrapping their invocation with GtpAdapter with the option
-lowercase.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Move menu item Reattach Program from Program to Tools menu.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu items Tools / Save Parameters and Reattach With Parameters.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Show stderr output of program in GTP shell, even if the engine is not
processing a command (e.g. because it is pondering while waiting for the
next command)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item File / Export / PNG Image.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: handle Go games in XML format. TwoGtp: new option -xml.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: mark points on board if text is selected in the GtpShell that
contains points (like it is already done with text selection in comment
or in text windows created by analyze commands)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: option -analyze is no longer supported
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpAdapter: option -resign is no longer supported
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Rename command line tools using prefix gogui- to avoid conflict with
tools from other packages.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Replace sgftotex by gogui-convert, which can read SGF or XML files and
supports several output formats
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fast forward or backward if shift key is pressed while the mouse wheel is used
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-thumbnail: new option -scale
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-twogtp: also measure real time used by programs.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-statistics: new option -random
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Automatically restore clock to current node, if it was never running.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Partial translation of the user interface into German. New menu item
Help/Switch Language to select the default language.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Ask user whether to continue, if a command in a file sent with "Send File"
fails.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use orange color for standard error lines in GTP Shell that start with
"warning:"
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

</revhistory>
</para>
</appendix>
