<appendix id="news">
<title>Release Notes</title>
<para>
<revhistory>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2.2</revnumber>
<date>19 Aug 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Don't automatically round the komi to a multiple of 0.5 anymore and show
a warning, if an SGF contains a komi that is not a multiple of 0.5
(bug #2990714)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Change Java2D rendering on Windows from DDraw to GDI to avoid repaint
errors
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Make gogui-adapter correctly forward resign responses to genmove commands
(bug #3016960)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Update some standard icons to Tango icons from freedesktop.org
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Replaced some simple text files in the distribution, like README and INSTALL,
by HTML.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Other small fixes
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2.1</revnumber>
<date>20 Apr 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix clearing of board markup if the caret in the comment field or GTP shell
changes and no text was selected before and after the change. This made
using SQUARE and other markup commands in Live Gfx unusable, because the
markup was immediately cleared after the next line from the program's standard
error was received. (bug #2964755)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix capitalization of open button tooltip
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix NullPointerException that occured during exporting a PNG image if board
labels existed (bug #2989711)
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
<date>28 Feb 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use more meaningful system properties for displaying the Java runtime name
and version in the about and crash dialog (java.runtime.name instead of
java.vm.name, if existing, and java.version instead of java.vm.version)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Look for strings like "Black to play" when importing positions from text
diagrams.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp: use a lock file to check that TwoGtp is not already running with the
same result file.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp: write game number to standard error at beginning of a game, if option
-verbose is used.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item Find Next Comment
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix parsing of OT property in SGF files that erroneously interpreted Japanese
byoyomi as Canadian overtime (which is currently the only time system supported
by GTP and GoGui)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Allow to use Reattach Parameters if program is dead but parameter snapshot
exists
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGuiAdapter: forward kgs-genmove_cleanup to the program if it supports it
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Small fixes
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2pre2</revnumber>
<date>08 Jan 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix bug in last release that made GoGui crash if it was started with no
program attached (bug #2928104)
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2pre1</revnumber>
<date>03 Jan 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Add notes about OpenJDK and Ubuntu 9.10 in the README file.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Don't synchronize the program with GTP commands immediately after navigation
in the game tree but only when needed. This speeds up navigation and keeps
the GTP log shorter.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Simplify context menu of a point on the board by removing analyze commands
with point argument
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Support multi-line text in analyze commands of type gfx
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New checkbox Reuse text window in analyze dialog
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item: Import SGF from Clipboard
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu items: Snapshot Parameters, Restore Parameters
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Enable parameter commands in menu only if the currently attached program
has analyze commands of type "param"
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
System look and feel is now used by default on Linux, since the GTK-based
system look and feel in newer versions on the JRE has good usability now;
the JGoodies Looks look and feel is no longer used
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
No longer install MIME type definition for KDE 3 in installation script on
Unix; new version of KDE now support the standard shared MIME database from
freedesktop.org
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Default installation directory in install.sh is now /usr/local
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
<date>09 Jul 2008</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use Java 5 language features; older Java versions are no longer supported.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Remove the GmpToGtp adapter, because the Go Modem Protocol and usage of
serial ports have become quite obsolete. Should there still be use cases, then
a version of GmpToGtp from previous GoGui releases can still be used in
combination with a newer version of the GoGui interface.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use uppercase letters for color arguments in GTP commands (like play or
gogui-setup). This was changed for consistency with the convention in the user
interface. It could break programs that do not treat colors in a
case-insensitive way (in violation of the GTP specification). Such programs can
still be used by wrapping their invocation with GtpAdapter with the option
-lowercase.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Move menu item Reattach Program from Program to Tools menu.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu items Tools / Save Parameters and Reattach With Parameters.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Show stderr output of program in GTP shell, even if the engine is not
processing a command (e.g. because it is pondering while waiting for the
next command)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item File / Export / PNG Image.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: handle Go games in XML format. TwoGtp: new option -xml.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: mark points on board if text is selected in the GtpShell that
contains points (like it is already done with text selection in comment
or in text windows created by analyze commands)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: option -analyze is no longer supported
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpAdapter: option -resign is no longer supported
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Rename command line tools using prefix gogui- to avoid conflict with
tools from other packages.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Replace sgftotex by gogui-convert, which can read SGF or XML files and
supports several output formats
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fast forward or backward if shift key is pressed while the mouse wheel is used
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-thumbnail: new option -scale
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-twogtp: also measure real time used by programs.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-statistics: new option -random
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Automatically restore clock to current node, if it was never running.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Partial translation of the user interface into German. New menu item
Help/Switch Language to select the default language.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Ask user whether to continue, if a command in a file sent with "Send File"
fails.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use orange color for standard error lines in GTP Shell that start with
"warning:"
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
<date>29 Aug 2007</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New optional commands for setting up positions; see section Setup Commands
in the manual
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The preferred way to configure analyze commands is now that the program
implements the command gogui-analyze_commands, otherwise an internal list with
some standard commands and GNU Go extensions is used.
If gogui-analyze_commands is supported, only the response will be used to
configure analyze commands, so that the Go engine has full control over what
is shown in what order in the analyze dialog.
Analyze command configuration files in the .gogui directory are no longer
supported; the only way to use external configuration files is to invoke
GoGui with the option -analyze-commands.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The following GoGui extension commands use the prefix gogui- now according to
the GTP standard for extension commands: gogui-play_sequence,
gogui-analyze_commands, gogui-interrupt, gogui-sigint, gogui-title.
The old versions (play_sequence, gogui_analyze_commands, gogui_interrupt,
gogui_sigint, gogui_title) are deprecated and may not be supported in the
future.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use platform specific storage of preferences; don't use .gogui/config
anymore
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use set_free_handicap if supported by the Go engine
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Several changes in the organization of the user interface
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Remove menu item Configure Analyze / Only Supported Commands; this is the
default and only behaviour now
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Remove menu item Game / Cleanup; GoGui will now always use kgs-genmove_cleanup
commands if play is continued after game has ended and program supports
kgs-genmove_cleanup
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The scoring_system command and GoGui option -rules are no longer supported
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Import Go positions in text format from files or clipboard
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Allow setup stones in non-root position
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Don't use default komi anymore if game is loaded with unknown komi
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Store lost on time information in game result
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Analyze command wildcard %f is deprecated; use new wildcards %r and %w instead
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Don't show error anymore for programs that don't support undo, automatically
synchronize position from start instead
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use same handicap locations as in GTP specification
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item Export Text Position to Clipboard
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use Quaqua look and feel on Mac OS/X
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
LaTeX position export now exports all markup types
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpAdapter: handle all state changing commands and automatically emulate them
if not supported by the engine; always translate a loadsgf command into a
sequence of play commands; don't use option -emuloadsgf and -emuhandicap
anymore
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpDummy: new option -resign
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpDisplay: support resign
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui, GtpDisplay: don't support option -fast anymore
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp: new option -maxmoves
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpRegress: support for test files not in the current directory
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp: option -loadsgf no longer exists; programs should implement
gogui-play_sequence if the transmission of openings with many stones or moves
is slow
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpServer: new option -timeout
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Other changes, fixes and user interface re-organizations
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: automatically clear markup on the board at the start of a Live Graphics
command. GtpDisplay: support Live Graphics.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: allow going forward/backward with the mouse wheel
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui, TwoGtp: support time specs using seconds in option -time
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpRegress: new option -gtpfile; support for test suites (files containing
lists of test files)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Update license to GPL version 3
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: send time settings and komi before setup stones and moves
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New parameter type "list" for analyze commands of type "param".
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>0.9</revnumber>
<date>15 May 2006</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: new default look and feel PlasticXP from jgoodies.com on Linux
and Windows; speed up board repaint; don't use DirectDraw on Windows anymore
to avoid screen flicker
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: performance improvements in communication with the Go program
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: new extension command play_sequence is used if supported by the Go
program
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: new menu items "Play Single Move",
"Configure Board/Fixed Size Comment Font",
"Configure Tree/Show Subtree Sizes"
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: new extension command gogui_analyze_commands to query analyze commands
from the program
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: use Swing file dialog on Mac for file name parameters of analyze
commands again (native file dialogs need to know, if the file name is used
for load or save)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: remove support for section and scale parameters of analyze commands
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: allow keyboard navigation in game tree window
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpStatistics: make it work with protocol version 2 programs; new option
-setup
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp: new option -time
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New tool sgfthumbnail; make GoGui create thumbnails for opened or saved files
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: use JGoodies WindowsLookAndFeel as default on Windows
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: enable preview in file dialog on Windows
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: allow to display graphical data while a command is in progress;
see section Live Graphics in the documentation
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpStatistics: new options -min, -max, -backward
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpRegress: remove option -filecomments; use new tool GtpStatistics instead
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>0.8</revnumber>
<date>26 Nov 2005</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Move all classes to the namespace net.sf.gogui;
avoid using class names that are already used basic java packages,
like Color or Point.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Include Sun's implementation of the Java Communications API and the
Docbook XSL files in the distribution to make compilation easier.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: re-organize menu bar. New menu Bookmarks.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: use gg-undo, if available
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: new menu item Game/Cleanup
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: new analyze command types eplist (editable point lists) and gfx
(graphics).
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: new board context menu for quickly running analyze commands that need
one point and optionally one color argument.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: use dialogs for all secondary windows; they are always on top of the
main window now
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: load and save SGF marks and labels; edit them from context menu
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: new option Timestamp in GTP shell settings menu
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpRegress: return -1 if any unexpected fails occurred
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpRegress: include error response outputs in test summaries;
fix NullPointerException, if test file contains response pattern without
a command to test (simply ignore the pattern)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpAdapter: fix missing clear_board commands if -emuloadsgf is used
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpDummy: new option -srand
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpTerminal: fix exception if empty line is entered
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
NetGtp: new option -timeout
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp: remove option -estimate-score; use the new tool GtpStatistics instead
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp: fix wrong cputimes
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New tool GtpStatistics
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Numerous other fixes and improvements
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: more reorganization of the menu bar
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpAdapter: new option -lowercase
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp, GtpRegress: avoid locale-dependent formatting of some numbers in
output files which broke the HTML report generation.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item Export/Text Position
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

</revhistory>
</para>
</appendix>
