<appendix id="news">
<title>Release Notes</title>
<para>
<revhistory>

<revision>
<revnumber>&version;</revnumber>
<date></date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Added Slowenian translation. Thanks to Boris Mitrovic.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Reduced maximum height of dialogs for parameter analyze commands to fit
on smaller screens.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Ignore mouse wheel events while command in progress to avoid error dialogs
if multiple wheel events are generated and an auto-run analyze command is
still processing the last board change.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Added missing program argument to man pages of gogui-adapter and
gogui-terminal.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-terminal: fixed bug that caused a crash in load command; write error
message if undo command has arguments
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Typos fixed in German internationalization.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-twogtp: do not create a lock file if option -sgffile is not used;
fix broken writing to result file on Windows
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: new option -register
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2.3</revnumber>
<date>25 Oct 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fixed wrong parsing of escaped linebreaks in SGF files that could cause
wrong reading of SGF files (bug #3050997)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Made remembering of "Show Info Panel" setting on startup work.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Work around a bug in OpenJDK 1.6.0_20 on Linux that made the saving of
GoGui's settings fail.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2.2</revnumber>
<date>19 Aug 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Don't automatically round the komi to a multiple of 0.5 anymore and show
a warning, if an SGF contains a komi that is not a multiple of 0.5
(bug #2990714)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Change Java2D rendering on Windows from DDraw to GDI to avoid repaint
errors
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Make gogui-adapter correctly forward resign responses to genmove commands
(bug #3016960)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Update some standard icons to Tango icons from freedesktop.org
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Replaced some simple text files in the distribution, like README and INSTALL,
by HTML.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Other small fixes
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2.1</revnumber>
<date>20 Apr 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix clearing of board markup if the caret in the comment field or GTP shell
changes and no text was selected before and after the change. This made
using SQUARE and other markup commands in Live Gfx unusable, because the
markup was immediately cleared after the next line from the program's standard
error was received. (bug #2964755)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix capitalization of open button tooltip
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix NullPointerException that occured during exporting a PNG image if board
labels existed (bug #2989711)
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
<date>28 Feb 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use more meaningful system properties for displaying the Java runtime name
and version in the about and crash dialog (java.runtime.name instead of
java.vm.name, if existing, and java.version instead of java.vm.version)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Look for strings like "Black to play" when importing positions from text
diagrams.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp: use a lock file to check that TwoGtp is not already running with the
same result file.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
TwoGtp: write game number to standard error at beginning of a game, if option
-verbose is used.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item Find Next Comment
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix parsing of OT property in SGF files that erroneously interpreted Japanese
byoyomi as Canadian overtime (which is currently the only time system supported
by GTP and GoGui)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Allow to use Reattach Parameters if program is dead but parameter snapshot
exists
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGuiAdapter: forward kgs-genmove_cleanup to the program if it supports it
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Small fixes
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2pre2</revnumber>
<date>08 Jan 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fix bug in last release that made GoGui crash if it was started with no
program attached (bug #2928104)
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.2pre1</revnumber>
<date>03 Jan 2010</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Add notes about OpenJDK and Ubuntu 9.10 in the README file.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Don't synchronize the program with GTP commands immediately after navigation
in the game tree but only when needed. This speeds up navigation and keeps
the GTP log shorter.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Simplify context menu of a point on the board by removing analyze commands
with point argument
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Support multi-line text in analyze commands of type gfx
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New checkbox Reuse text window in analyze dialog
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item: Import SGF from Clipboard
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu items: Snapshot Parameters, Restore Parameters
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Enable parameter commands in menu only if the currently attached program
has analyze commands of type "param"
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
System look and feel is now used by default on Linux, since the GTK-based
system look and feel in newer versions on the JRE has good usability now;
the JGoodies Looks look and feel is no longer used
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
No longer install MIME type definition for KDE 3 in installation script on
Unix; new version of KDE now support the standard shared MIME database from
freedesktop.org
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Default installation directory in install.sh is now /usr/local
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
<date>09 Jul 2008</date>
<authorinitials>enz</authorinitials>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use Java 5 language features; older Java versions are no longer supported.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Remove the GmpToGtp adapter, because the Go Modem Protocol and usage of
serial ports have become quite obsolete. Should there still be use cases, then
a version of GmpToGtp from previous GoGui releases can still be used in
combination with a newer version of the GoGui interface.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use uppercase letters for color arguments in GTP commands (like play or
gogui-setup). This was changed for consistency with the convention in the user
interface. It could break programs that do not treat colors in a
case-insensitive way (in violation of the GTP specification). Such programs can
still be used by wrapping their invocation with GtpAdapter with the option
-lowercase.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Move menu item Reattach Program from Program to Tools menu.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu items Tools / Save Parameters and Reattach With Parameters.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Show stderr output of program in GTP shell, even if the engine is not
processing a command (e.g. because it is pondering while waiting for the
next command)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
New menu item File / Export / PNG Image.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: handle Go games in XML format. TwoGtp: new option -xml.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: mark points on board if text is selected in the GtpShell that
contains points (like it is already done with text selection in comment
or in text windows created by analyze commands)
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GoGui: option -analyze is no longer supported
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
GtpAdapter: option -resign is no longer supported
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Rename command line tools using prefix gogui- to avoid conflict with
tools from other packages.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Replace sgftotex by gogui-convert, which can read SGF or XML files and
supports several output formats
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Fast forward or backward if shift key is pressed while the mouse wheel is used
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-thumbnail: new option -scale
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-twogtp: also measure real time used by programs.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
gogui-statistics: new option -random
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Automatically restore clock to current node, if it was never running.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Partial translation of the user interface into German. New menu item
Help/Switch Language to select the default language.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Ask user whether to continue, if a command in a file sent with "Send File"
fails.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use orange color for standard error lines in GTP Shell that start with
"warning:"
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

</revhistory>
</para>
</appendix>
